Guide to the Public Art Fund Archive MSS.270
Fales Library and Special Collections
Public Art Fund Archive
1966-2022, October 2025-ongoing
Fales Library and Special Collections
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.)
MSS.270
171.67 Linear Feet in 153 record cartons, 80 manuscript boxes, 12 photo binders, 32 film cans, 20 flat boxes, 4 rolled storage boxes, 3 flat file folders, 2 card boxes, 16 VHS cases, 1 media box, 1 oversize portfolio, and 1 folder in shared housing
1 websites in 1 archived website.
Founded in 1977, the Public Art Fund is an independent, not-for-profit organization dedicated to presenting works of contemporary art at public sites throughout New York City. The materials in the collection are the primary documentation of hundreds of Public Art Fund exhibitions, featuring artists such as: Louise Bourgeois, Chris Burden, Keith Haring, Jenny Holzer, William Kentridge, Jeff Koons, Richard Prince, Pipilotti Rist, Kiki Smith, David Wojnarowicz, and Martin Wong, among others. The collection also documents the history of founder Doris C. Freedman and her work with two pioneering arts organizations that were precursors to the Public Art Fund: City Walls and the Public Arts Council.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Public Art Fund donated their archives to NYU in April of 2010. Prior to the donation, the collection was removed from storage in 2007, overseen by archivists David Kim and Tara Hart, who worked on the collection over the course of three years with the help of a team of graduate student interns.
Accretions were donated by Public Art Fund in 2013, 2015, and 2025; the accession numbers associated with these additions are 2013.270, 2015.270, and 2025.014, respectively.
https://www.publicartfund.org/ was selected by the Fales curator and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with this website is 2026.003.
Arrangement
Efforts were made to preserve the original arrangement of the collection. Within each series, most items are arranged chronologically, when material is dated.
Within Series I, Series II, and Series VI, materials are arranged chronologically. Materials in Series III, Series IV, and Series VIII reflect the original order of the creator. Materials in Series V: Messages to the Public are arranged alphabetically by artist's surname. Series XV is arranged alphabetically.
The Public Art Fund Archive is organized into the following fourteen series:
Series Arrangement
Series I: City Walls
Series II: Public Arts Council
Series III: Percent for Art
Series IV: Director's Files
Series V: Messages to the Public
Series VI: Public Art Fund - Project Files
Series VII: Public Art Fund - Publicity, Publication, and Promotion
Series VIII: Susan Freedman Papers
Series IX: Photographic Material
Series X: Video
Series XI: Film
Series XII: Audio
Series XIII: Data Storage
Series XIV: Objects
Series XV: Printed Material
Series XVI" Archived Website
Oversize Series I: City Walls
Oversize Series II: Public Arts Council
Oversize Series VI: Project Files
Oversize Series VII: Publicity, Publication, and Promotion
Oversize Series IX: Photographic Material
For series and subseries descriptions, scroll down to Container List.
Scope and Contents
The Public Art Fund Archive is an expansive collection that documents over 30 years of Public Art Fund activity. Through correspondence, invoices, financial documents, contracts, drawings and site plans, photographs, announcements, ephemera, news clippings, articles, a website, and publicity reports, the archive provides a detailed account of the mechanisms involved in producing public art exhibitions. The material in the collection reflects how the organization supports its mission on all levels: curatorial, logistical, promotional and financial.
The collection also documents the history of founder Doris C. Freedman, her work with City Walls, Public Arts Council, and New York City's Percent for Art program. Overall, this collection provides valuable insight into the changing scope of contemporary public art practice in New York City from the 1970s to the present.
Historical Note
Public Art Fund is an independent non-profit organization dedicated to working with emerging and established artists to produce exhibitions of contemporary art throughout New York City. The history organization is aligned with the history of founder Doris C. Freedman (1928-1981), a social worker and supporter of public art who served as the first New York City Director of Cultural Affairs during the Lindsay Administration. In the late 1960s Freedman served as president of City Walls, an organization dedicated to providing artists with opportunities to create and display art in public settings, with a particular emphasis on producing public murals throughout New York City. In 1972 Freedman founded the Public Art Council as part of the Municipal Art Society. In 1977, an increasing volume of inquiries from artists prompted Freedman to form the Public Art Fund by consolidating the efforts of City Walls and the Public Arts Council.
Public Art Fund For over 30 years the Public Art Fund has worked to produce exhibitions of contemporary art at sites throughout New York City. The Public Art Fund was established in 1977 by Doris C. Freedman, who served as New York City's first Director of Cultural Affairs during the Lindsay Administration and additionally as the President of the Municipal Art Society. The formation of the Public Art Fund consolidated the efforts of two organizations: City Walls and The Public Arts Council of the Municipal Art Society. Both organizations sponsored a number of projects aimed at cultivating relationships between artists and communities, including Tony Rosenthal's "The Alamo" and Richard Haas' "Arcade." An increasing volume of public art inquiries and proposals prompted Freedman to form the Public Art Fund, merging the activities of both groups. The generative concept behind the Public Art Fund was to provide support to artists on every level: curatorial, logistical, promotional and financial. Over the years, public sites such as Doris Freedman Plaza, Rockefeller Center, and City Hall Park have been programmed on an ongoing basis. Other locations are selected for individual projects and programs on a case-by-case basis. In 1982, the Public Art Fund began a program called "Messages to the Public", which gave artists access to the Spectacolor lightboard at New York City's Times Square. From 1982-1990 over 70 artists broadcast 30-second computer-generated messages on the 800-square foot animated light board. This included works by Vito Acconci, Guerrilla Girls, Keith Haring, Jenny Holzer, Richard Prince, Tim Rollins and K.O.S., Christy Rupp, Kiki Smith, David Wojnarowicz, and Martin Wong, among others. In 1995, the Public Art Fund began its "In the Public Realm" program, offering emerging artists the opportunity to create art projects by responding to an open call for proposals. As of 2011, the Public Art Fund has worked with over 500 emerging and established artists and continues to bring artwork outside of the traditional context of museums and galleries, providing "a unique platform for an unparalleled public encounter with the art of our time." Projects include Janet Cardiff's "Her Long Black Hair" (2005), Chris Burden's "What My Dad Gave Me" (2008) and Olafur Eliasson's "The New York City Waterfalls" (2008). Funding is received through contributions from individuals, foundations, corporations, and with funds allocated from: the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs, New York State Council on the Arts, and the National Endowment for the Arts.
City Walls City Walls was incorporated as a not-for-profit in 1969 by a group of established professional artists. Working with artists and communities, City Walls was dedicated to revitalizing the visual environment of New York City through public art. Viewing the city as a work of art, the organization sponsored more than fifty murals by twenty-eight different artists. Early members and artists included Nassos Daphnis, Allan D'Arcangelo, Jason Crum, Mel Pekarsky, Tania, Robert Wiegand, and Todd Williams. Doris C. Freedman served as president of City Walls from 1971 to 1980.
Public Arts Council The Public Arts Council was formed in 1971 under the auspices of the Municipal Art Society of New York City. The advisory board was composed of professional artists, architects, city planners, developers and representatives from other organizations that dealt with public art. Over the years, the Public Arts Council served as "an advocate group for public art, as an administrative organization for initiating coordinating public art projects, and as a resource and information center for artists, city and community organizations, and educational institutions." The program was supported in through grants from the National Endowment for the Arts, the New York State Council on the Arts, the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs, and from private donations.
Percent for Art New York City adopted its Percent for Art legislation in 1982, requiring that one percent of the budget for eligible City-funded construction projects be allocated to commission or purchase public art works for city facilities. Doris Freedman helped to draft New York City's Percent for Art legislation and played a major role in lobbying the City Council. Deputy Mayor Ronay Menschel and Chief of Staff Diane Coffey were also key advocates. Mayor Edward Koch was in office to sign and pass the bill in 1982 and in 1983 the law went into effect. The program was initially administered by Public Art Fund until the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs assumed full responsibility in 1986. After this, the Public Art Fund ceased to save files pertaining to Percent for Art, until deaccessioning research began in 1994.
Doris C. Freedman Doris C. Freedman (1928-1981) served as New York City's first Director of Cultural Affairs during the Lindsay administration. A supporter of New York City's Percent for Art legislation, Freedman was dedicated to securing a place for contemporary art in a public setting while combining the interests of artists, urban planners, local communities, city agencies and public and private organizations. In 1971, Freedman founded the Public Arts Council and served as president of City Walls Inc. Under her leadership, both the Public Arts Council and City Walls provided technical assistance and financial support for a wide variety of projects, and developed programs to explore the potential of urban public spaces. In 1977 Freedman merged the efforts of City Walls and the Public Arts Council to create the Public Art Fund.
Susan K. Freedman Susan K. Freedman, daughter of founder Doris Freedman, has served as president of the Public Art Fund since 1986. As her biography at the Public Art Fund web site reads: "Freedman graduated from Brown University in 1982 with a B.A. in Studio Art and American Civilization, and was Assistant to Mayor Edward I. Koch, and Director of Special Projects and Events for the Art Commission of the City of New York from 1983 to 1986. Susan currently serves as Mayor Bloomberg's Representative on the Board of Trustees at the Museum of Modern Art, as well as on the Boards of the Municipal Art Society and WNYC Radio, and as Vice President of the Board for the City Parks Foundation. Most recently, Susan has joined the City of New York Department of Cultural Affairs Advisory Commission, and was a jury member for the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation's World Trade Center Memorial competition. She received the Municipal Art Society's Evangeline Blashfield Award in 2005."
Staff List: 1977-1981: Doris C. Freedman, President; 1982-1985: Jenny Dixon, Director; 1986-present: Susan K. Freedman, President; 1989-1995: James Clark, Director; 1996-2005: Tom Eccles, Director; 2005-2009: Rochelle Steiner, Director; 2009-present: Nicholas Baume, Director.
Bibliography:
Sources
Ault, J., Social Text Collective., & Drawing Center (New York, N.Y.). (2002). Alternative art, New York, 1965-1985: A cultural politics book for the Social Text Collective. New York: Drawing Center.
Brenson, Michael. "WHAT'S NEW AROUND TOWN IN OUTDOOR SCULPTURE. " New York Times. 19 Jul 1985, Late Edition (East Coast): Banking Information Source, ProQuest. Web. 16 Nov. 2010.
Breslaur, Jan. "A Spectacle of L.A. Art in New York's Times Square Advertising: California artists have been decorating a billboard with "Messages to the Public," but loss of funding threatens the project :[Home Edition]. " Los Angeles Times (pre-1997 Fulltext) 24 Nov. 1989,Los Angeles Times, ProQuest. Web. 16 Nov. 2010.
Doris C. Freedman Gallery, & Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1982). Ten years of public art, 1972-1982. Doris C. Freedman Gallery at the Urban Center, 457 Madison Avenue, New York, 20 May-18 June 1982. New York, N.Y.: Public Art Fund.
Freedman, S. K. (2004). Plop: Recent projects of the Public Art Fund. London: Merrell Publishers in association with Public Art Fund, New York.
Glueck, Grace. "What Part should the Public Play in Choosing Public Art?" New York Times. 3 Feb. 1985, Late Edition (East Coast): Banking Information Source, ProQuest. Web. 16 Nov. 2010.
McGill, Douglas C.. "In East Harlem, First 'Percent' Art." New York Times. 27 Jun 1985, Late Edition (East Coast): Banking Information Source, ProQuest. Web. 16 Nov. 2010.
Percent for Art. (2010). Retrieved November 12, 2010 from http://www.nyc.gov/html/dcla/html/panyc/panyc.shtml
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1980s). Newsletter. New York, N.Y.: Public Art Fund.
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1989). Issues, public art. New York City: Public Art Fund.
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1991). In process: The quarterly newsletter of the Public Art Fund Inc. New York, NY: Public Art Fund.
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1992). Public art issues. New York, NY: Public Art Fund.
Public Art Fund (New York, N.Y.). (1999). Public Art Fund, Inc. Retrieved January 1st, 2010, from http://www.publicartfund.org
Vogel, Carol. "Inside Art :[Leisure/Weekend Desk]. " New York Times. 27 Feb. 1998, Late Edition (East Coast): Banking Information Source, ProQuest. Web. 05 Nov. 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Materials at Fales Library and Special Collections
The Creative Time Archives, 1973-2006
The Fashion Moda Archive, 1978-1993
Harold and Joyce Pomeroy Schwartz Public Art Archive (unprocessed)
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Newsletters.; Résumés (personnel records); Reports.; Color negatives.; Purchase orders.; Receipts.; Periodicals; Politics in art.; Posters.; Community arts projects -- United States.; Legal correspondence.; Printed ephemera.; T-shirts; Group work in art.; Printed materials.; Grant proposals.; Public art -- New York (N.Y.); Public art spaces.; Public sculpture, American.; Publicizing.; Legal documents.; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Floppy disks.; New York (N.Y.).; Moving images.; Photographic prints.; Drawings; Photocopies.; Records (documents); Exhibition catalogs.; Non-profit artists centers.; Newspapers.; Artists and community -- United States; Installations (Art) -- United States.; Gay activists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Magnetic tapes.; Minorities in art.; Mini-DV.; Color slides.; Tax records.; Correspondence.; Financial records; Art, American -- New York (State) -- New York -- 21st century; Art and society -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Artists -- United States.; Feminism and art.; Audiocassettes.; Asian American artists -- Exhibitions; Press releases.; Audiovisual materials.; Audiotapes.; Alternative spaces (Arts facilities); AIDS (Disease) and art -- United States.; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); Black-and-white negatives.; CD-Rs.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Art -- Exhibitions -- New York (N.Y.); Public architecture.; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Exhibitions; Contracts; Community development, Urban; Women artists -- Exhibitions.; Women's rights.; Washington Square (New York, N.Y.); Women artists -- United States.; East Village (New York, N.Y.); Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Urban transportation.; Video art -- United States.; Videocassettes.; Social problems in art.; Contact sheets.; Super 8; Super-VHS (TM); Safe sex in AIDS prevention.; Artists -- Exhibitions; DeJong, Constance; Gran Fury (Artists' collective); ACT UP New York (Organization); Hammer, Barbara; Haring, Keith; Group Material (Firm: New York, N.Y.); Guerrilla Girls (Group of artists); Holzer, Jenny, 1950-; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Cardiff, Janet, 1957-; Casebere, James; Deacon, Richard, 1949-; Botero, Fernando, 1932-; Bourgeois, Louise, 1911-2010; Burden, Chris, 1946-; Chang, Jackie; Tillman, Lynne; Goldsworthy, Andy, 1956-; Foreman, Richard; Whitney Museum of American Art; Di Suvero, Mark, 1933-; Dion, Mark, 1961-; Freedman, Doris Chanin, 1928-1981; Freedman, Susan, 1970-; Otterness, Tom, 1952-; Paik, Nam June, 1932-2006; New York (N.Y.). Department of Cultural Affairs; Simmons, Laurie; Steir, Pat, 1940-; Gonzalez-Torres, Félix, 1957-1996; Wong, Martin; Kruger, Barbara, 1945-; Živančević, Nina, 1957-; ACT UP (Organization); Acconci, Vito, 1940-; LeWitt, Sol, 1928-2007; Lower Manhattan Cultural Council; Wojnarowicz, David; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013; Hershman-Leeson, Lynn, 1941-; National Endowment for the Arts; Kusama, Yayoi; Kapoor, Anish, 1954-; Dixon, Jenny; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Clark, James M.; Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-1988; Pepper, Beverly; Steiner, Rochelle; McCarthy, Paul; Baume, Nicholas; Muniz, Vik; New York State Council on the Arts; Koons, Jeff, 1955-; Eccles, Tom, 1964-; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1927; Weiner, Lawrence, 1942 February 10; Piper, Adrian, 1948-; Smith, Kiki, 1954-; Smith, Allison, 1972-; Simpson, Lorna, 1960-; Serra, Richard, 1938-; Rupp, Christy, 1949-; Rist, Pipilotti, 1962-; Rosler, Martha; Boltanski, Christian, 1944-; Dwyer, Nancy; Aycock, Alice; Indiana, Robert, 1928-2018; General Idea; Zittel, Andrea, 1965-; Whiteread, Rachel, 1963-; Creative Time, Inc.; West, Franz, 1947-
- Series I: City Walls
  Scope and Content
  This series documents the activities of City Walls Inc. Materials include administrative documents, financial records, plans, drawings, publications and photographs that provide insight into the planning, execution, and dismantling of the City Walls mural projects. The files are arranged chronologically. Series I is broken down into three subseries.
  - Subseries I.A: Administrative Files, 1967-1978; 1 boxes
    This series includes general correspondence, tax returns, financial records, consulting files, and general publicity efforts during the period from 1968 to 1978. This series also contains some of the background documentation in obtaining wall locations for murals.
    - Statements and Descriptions, 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tax Returns/Financial Statements, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tours, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Tax exempt certificates, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Tax forms, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Silkscreen of Walls- c&d editions, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Posters of Walls/City Walls Environmental Art As Supergraphics, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board of Directors/info/notes/memos/minutes, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cooper-Hewitt sculpture symposium/community sculpture, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - John Canaday article and responses, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Consulting - Detroit Institute of Fine Arts, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tax returns, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Proposals, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Consulting - New Jersey Department of Community Affairs, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Tax returns, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Slides - sales & loans, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Serigraph - Richard Anaszkiewicz, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Technical information for painting walls, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Photographers, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Possible/Available walls, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Tax returns, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Consulting/ Greater Urban Walls - Atlanta, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Tax returns, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Tax forms / United States Corporation company Dover Delaware franchise, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Release forms, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)